Guide to the Young Men's--Young Women's Christian Association at Duke University records, 1968-1979
Duke University. University Archives
Young Men's--Young Women's Christian Association at Duke University records 1968-1979
Duke University. University Archives
YM-YWCA at Duke University.
3.0 linear feet Extent: 1,000 Items
The Young Men's-Young Women's Christian Association was created in 1969, an apparent merger of the men's and women's Y's elements. The YM-YWCA was a student religious organization operating within the Religious Activities Department and overseen by an advisory board and advised by the Associate Directors of Religious Activities. The collection contains material pertaining to the activities and organization of the YM-YWCA including annual reports, flyers, handbooks, directories, and materials documenting the joint efforts of the YMCA and YWCA around the same period. The dates in the collection range from circa 1968-1979.
UA.31.04.0015
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Provenance
The Young Men's--Young Women's Christian Association at Duke University records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1975-1978, 1983.
Historical Note
A student religious organization operating within the Religious Activities Department and overseen by an advisory board and advised by the Associate Directors of Religious Activities. The YM-YWCA was created in 1969 in an apparent merger of elements of the men's and women's Y's. Among the activities undertaken by the organization were draft counseling, the promotion of vocation for social change, support and/or sponsorship of Black Days in Durham and selective buying campaigns, an international Christmas Bazaar, and the sponsorship of films and presentation of lectures by activists such as Dave Dellinger, Reed Kramer, Ben Ruffin, and Rennie Davis. The organization apparently ceased functioning around 1980-1981.
Collection Overview
Collection contains material pertaining to the activities and organization of the YM-YWCA, a social activist religious group, including annual reports, flyers, handbooks, directories, and materials documenting the joint efforts of the YMCA and YWCA around the same period. Includes the logbook (1972/1973; restricted) and related material of the organization’s Draft Counseling and Information Center; "A White Paper on Institutional Racism at Duke: The Curriculum" (1972); listings of vocations for social change produced by OPT, its center for social change information; and copies of the handbook, The University Experience (1969/1970-1978/1979). The handbooks include essays on race relations, sexuality, civil rights and social change, and the experiences of foreign and minority students, as well as University history and administrative information. In an annual report (1970/1971) the book is said to have changed from "a book of interesting facts and figures" to "a rather controversial" alternative view of the University.
Also present in the collection are the records of the Institute for Nonviolent Study and Action (INSA) which was a leftist, activist agency of the Duke YM-YWCA. Their records include brochures, flyers, newsletters, manuals, and information concerning political and social issues of the early 1970s, and activities of the INSA. A sampling of topics include: Buddhism and nonviolence, Indochina; history, politics, and culture during the war, Cuba, UMWA (United Mine Workers Association), University investment, War -- bombing effects, and Wounded Knee. The INSA also collected flyers, brochures, and other printed matter from national organizations. Some organizations include: Committee on New Alternatives in the Middle East, Gandhi Peace Foundation, Vietnam Veterans Against the War, and New American Movement.
Collection Arrangement
The collection is arranged into the following series: Institute for nonviolent study and action, circa 1968-1975, National Organizations, 1970-1973, Duke YM-YWCA, 1968-1979.
Subject Headings
African Americans -- North Carolina -- Durham -- Rallies, demonstrations, etc.; College students -- Political activity -- North Carolina -- Durham; College students -- North Carolina -- Durham -- Sexual behavior; Duke University -- Handbooks, manuals, etc.; Duke University -- Students -- Public services; Duke University -- Religious activities; Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975 -- Protest movements; Young Men's Christian Association; Young Women's Christian Association
Related Material
Young Women's Christian Association. Duke University Chapter records, 1908-1971.
University Archive, Duke University.
Young Men's Christian Association. Duke University Chapter records, 1920-1969.
University Archive, Duke University.
Contents of Collection
- Institute for nonviolent study and action, circa 1968-1975, 1 Box
  The Institute for Nonviolent Study and Action was a leftist, activist agency of the Duke YM-YWCA. This series include brochures, flyers, manuals, and information concerning political and social issues of the early 1970s, and activities of the INSA.
  - Amnesty, 1973 (Box 1)
  - AROD (Army Research Office - Durham), 1970-1972 (Box 1)
  - Bibliographies, 1970-1973 (Box 1)
  - Buddhism and nonviolence, 1970s (Box 1)
  - Calendars, minutes, announcements, agendas, etc., 1970s (Box 1)
  - Campus Recruiting, 1971-1973 (Box 1)
  - Chile Symposium, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Control Data Corp. (C.D.C.), 1972 (Box 1)
  - Cuba, 1974 (Box 1)
  - DMS (Defense/Aerospace Contract Quarters), 1970-1972 (Box 1)
  - Fasts and Fasting, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Films, 1973-1975 (Box 1)
  - Film series: orders, invoices, confirmations, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Ford Motor Company, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Guerilla Theater, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Honeywell (Box 1)
  - Indochina; history, politics, and culture during the war, 1968-1973 (Box 1)
  - Indochina War: overview and general, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - Indochina War: weapons, army strategies, air war, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - Industry involvement in military, 1971-1973 (Box 1)
  - IT and T (see Southern Africa), 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - Japan, 1970s (Box 1)
  - Literature Table: orders, invoices, correspondence, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - Jo Anne Little, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Lockheed Aircraft Corp., 1971 (Box 1)
  - Movin' On's, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Duke NAM Leaflets, 1974 (Box 1)
  - NAM organizing, 1972-1975 (Box 1)
  - Newspapers, 1972-1975 (Box 1)
  - NAM miscellaneous, 1972-1975 (Box 1)
  - Natural NAM - general correspondence, 1974 (Box 1)
  - N.C. Alliance, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Organizing manual draft, 1970s (Box 1)
  - Peace Unity News (Box 1)
  - Planned Poverty and Technical assistance, 1970s (Box 1)
  - "Political economy of sexism" -Somers and Johnson, 1970s (Box 1)
  - Political Education (Internal), 1974 (Box 1)
  - Student Network. Materials, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Training for nonviolent responses in social conflict, 1970s (Box 1)
  - Treaties and other international acts, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - UMWA (United Mine Workers Association) (Box 1)
  - University Investment, 1972 (Box 1)
  - War -- bombing effects, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Wounded Knee, 1973 (Box 1)
- National Organizations, 1970s, 2 Boxes
  This series include brochures, flyers, and information produced by national organizations and collected by the Institute for Nonviolent Study and Action concerning political and social issues of the early 1970s.
  - AFSC (American Friends Service Committee), 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - Another Mother for Peace, 1970/1972 (Box 1)
  - Anti-War Union, 1972 (Box 1)
  - A.P.G.A. Peace Commission, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Appalachian South Folklife Center, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Atlanta Workshop in Nonviolence, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Bay Area Nonviolent Community, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Center for Conflict Resolution (Madison), 1971-1973 (Box 1)
  - Center for the Study of Development and Social Change (Box 1)
  - The Christophers (Box 1)
  - Charleston (S.C.) G.I. Office (Box 1)
  - Churches of Christ, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Committee on New Alternatives in the Middle East, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Committee of Concerned Asian Scholars, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Community Concerns Committee: 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - Community Study Group, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Cuban Studies (Box 1)
  - Elections: 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - Episcopal Peace Fellowship (Box 1)
  - Fasting (Box 1)
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation, 1970-1972 (Box 1)
  - Friends Committee on National Legislation, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Gandhi Peace Foundation (India), 1972 (Box 1)
  - Greensboro Peace Center, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Greenville CALC (Clergy and Laity Concerned) (Box 1)
  - Institute for Nonviolent Study and Action, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - INSA Project Journal (Box 1)
  - INSA Workshop, Oct. 1972 (Box 1)
  - Institute for Study of Nonviolence (Palo Alto), 1970-1973 (Box 1)
  - Institute Mountain West, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Institute for Nonviolent Study and Action Veteran's Day Fast for Life, Oct. 20-23, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Jewish Peace Fellowship (Box 2)
  - Journal of World Education, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Vietnam Veterans Against the War, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Movement for a New Society (also AQAG), 1972 (Box 2)
  - War Resister's League, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - Shanti: Nonviolent Action Center (Fresno) and Joyas Struggle NRG, 1972 (Box 2)
  - National American Congress on Latin American (NaCLA) (Box 2)
  - Southern Conference Education Fund (SCEF) Louisville, KY, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - SCLC (Southern Christian Leadership Conference), 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - South Jersey Peace Center (Moorestown, NJ), 1972 (Box 2)
  - Sunflower Life Center (Newton, Kansas), 1972 (Box 2)
  - Third World Coalition, 1972 (Box 2)
  - The Martin Luther King Center for Social Change, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Nonviolent Action: Training (1970s) (Box 2)
  - Money, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Reports, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Mailing Lists, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - MNS Provisional Council Madison, Nov. 16-18, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Vietnam Children's Fund (Box 2)
  - Unsell the War (Box 2)
  - Times Change Press, 1971-1973 (Box 2)
  - Medical Aid for Indochina. Inc., (MAI), 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - Nonviolence Conference, Spring 1972 (Box 2)
  - Nonviolence Conference - Bills, Spring 1972 (Box 2)
  - Pacific Studies Center, 1972 (Box 2)
  - NC Political Prisoners Committee, 1972 (Box 2)
  - New World Coalition (Box 2)
  - New American Movement (Box 2)
  - National Peace Action Committee (Box 2)
  - National Emergency Civil Liberties Committee, 1972 (Box 2)
  - National Committee Against Repressive Legislation, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Peace Booth Committee, 1972 (Box 2)
  - NAM Records (Box 2)
  - University Experience, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Racism Workshop: 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Vocation for Social Change Conference, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Draft Counseling and Information Center Draft Counselors Log Book, 1972-1973--RESTRICTED (Box 2)
  - Women's Caucus of NAM (Box 2)
  - Workers Support Committee NAM (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Radical Education Project (Box 2)
  - Post American, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - Philadelphia Resistance, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - Philadelphia Life Center, 1972 (Box 2)
  - People's Bicentennial Commission, (P.B.C), 1972 (Box 2)
  - 1973-1974 (Box 2)
  - War Tax Resistance, 1971 (Box 2)
  - White House Daily Meeting, 1971-1972 (Box 2)
- Duke YM-YWCA, 1 Box
  Series contains material pertaining to the activities and organization of the YM-YWCA including annual reports, flyers, handbooks, directories, and materials documenting the joint efforts of the YMCA and YWCA around the same period.
  - Newspapers (Box 2)
  - A White Paper on Institutional Racism at Duke: the Curriculum, 1972 (Box 2)
  - YM-YWCA Annual Report (c.2), 1968/1969 - 1969/1970 (Box 2)
  - Flyers, Announcements, Clippings, 1979 (Box 2)
  - A.J. Muste "Of Holy Disobedience" (Box 2)
  - Draft Counseling and Information Center. Statements of Religious Bodies on the Conscientious Objector," ca. 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - OPT. Social Change Vocations - Directories, 1971 (Box 2)
  - OPT. Social Change Vocations - Directories, 1972 (Box 2)
  - The University Experience [Handbook], 1969/1970 - 1972/1973 (Box 2)
  - The University Experience [Handbook], 1973/1974-1978/1979 (Box 2)
  - The University Experience [Handbook], Duplicates (Box 2)
  - Duke YMCA/Duke YWCA: Joint Efforts: Community Action. Community Concerns Committee (Box 2)
  - Cabinet Meeting, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Campus Ministry: 1970-1971 (Box 2)